Finding Aid for John Abraham Van den Broek papers, 1905-1955
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John Abraham Van den Broek papers 1905-1955
Van den Broek, John Abraham, 1885-
0.5 linear feet (in 2 boxes)
86160 Aa 2
Professor of mechanical engineering at University of Michigan. Correspondence concerning University and departmental business, World War II research projects, the American Society of Civil Engineering, and research projects of the Hamilton Watch Company and Hayes Wheel Company.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Professor Van den Broek (donor no. 3583 ) and came to the library in 1959.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
John A. Van den Broek was born in Middleharnis, Holland on March 6, 1885. He emigrated to the United States in 1905. He received his B.S. degree from the University of Kansas in 1911 and his Ph.D. from the University of Michigan in 1918. Beginning in 1914, Van den Broek was a member of the faculty of the University. He became full professor of engineering mechanics in 1926. He was the author of professional monographs, including Elastic Energy Theory (1942) and Theory of Limit Design (1945). He died April 20, 1959.
The collection consists of correspondence and other professional materials, most relating to his research and other responsibilities at the University of Michigan. Of note are his Reports on automobile wheel tests for Hayes Wheel Company, 1923-1926, and a report on high strength aluminum alloys written during World War II.
Subjects:
American Society of Civil Engineers.; Automobile industry and trade--Michigan.; Clocks and watches.; Hamilton Watch Company.; Hayes Wheel Company (Jackson, Mich.); Jackson (Mich.); University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Research.; World War, 1939-1945--Education and the war.; World War, 1939-1945--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Van den Broek, John Abraham, 1885-
- Correspondence
  - Chronological
    - 1905-1925 (Box 1)
    - 1943 (Box 1)
    - January-May 1944 (Box 1)
    - June-July 1944 (Box 1)
    - August-December 1944 (Box 1)
    - January-April 1955 (Box 1)
    - 1946-1947 (Box 1)
    - 1948 (Box 1)
    - 1952-1955 (Box 1)
  - By topic
    - 1917-1949, re. university salary and appointments (Box 1)
    - 1939-1948, with students (Box 1)
    - 1945-1949, re. Column Research Council of the American Society of Civil Engineering (Box 1)
    - Correspondence with G.P. Luckey, Director of Research, Hamilton Watch Company, February 1932-January 1933, 4 folders (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Reports on automobile wheel tests for Hayes Wheel Company, 1923-1926, 5 volumes (Box 1)
  - Report on high strength aluminum alloys, ca. 1944 (Box 1)